tapering is incredibly effective at
enhancing performance because of the
basic model that we call Fitness minus
fatigue so your physical fitness
sometimes described as your V2 Max but
in this case even colloquially your
strength your agility your coordination
your skill all those things we'll just
call Fitness so your physical attributes
are actually pretty stable and
specifically your V2 Max and aerobic
endurance conditioning are quite stable
your fatigue though is highly transient
okay so think about it this way if you
took the day off today you would not get
any weaker you would not reduce your V2
Max nothing would change in your Fitness
however taking a single day off can
dramatically change your acute fatigue
some extra rest some more food can
absolutely a little bit of caffeine or
stimulant can immediately change your
perceived fatigue level so if we think
about fatigue being transient of course
you can be fatigued often for a long
period of time but the actual effects of
it are are transient they're acute
Fitness is pretty stable and so if we
know that we can say Okay prior to
competition we want to maximize our
fitness but reduce our fatigue so if we
give ourselves some more energy A couple
of days or so prior to competition and
we reduce fatigue we're not going to
compromise our fitness and therefore we
should perform at a higher level and the
literature will basically support that
in fact I'll just tell you right now
I'll jump the gun a little bit I don't
know of a single paper that has ever
appropriately designed a taper program
and failed to show benefits it is really
quite strong the well-roundedness and
support for the performance-enhancing
benefits of a reasonable taper what's a
reasonable taper mean and what are those
performance benefits it can be quite
extensive and it can range there are
studies showing up to a 28-day long
taper of up to 70% volume reduction
still don't come with performance drops
now it depends on how you're defining
performance so let's start talking
details so what do we know it's been
well documented a really nice review
from my friends Jimmy baggley and Kevin
murak called less is more the
physiological basis for tapering and
endurance strength and power athletes
it's a little bit older at this point I
think about nine years or so but it is a
really nice easy to read document that
is open access you can check you in that
paper you will see uh performance
benefits in cycling swimming running
rowing from the strength training side
weightlifting and powerlifting and
strong man Highland Games bodybuilding
even more recent research on CrossFit uh
Team Sports volleyball soccer rugby etc
etc and it all seems to show a positive
benefit from taper and the benefits are
really well-rounded so it actually comes
in what we call the whole body to Gene
to cell to everything else in between
there are molecular responses at the
single fiber level there are changes in
strength and performance and sporting
outcomes winning more games so on and so
forth so I'm so confident in these data
because it's been done in so many
populations in so many different
Laboratories in so many settings in so
many sports it's at the cellular level
it's at the performance level it's at
the psychological level and it is again
almost all pointing the same direction
which gives you tremendous confidence
that this is a real and is a really
important phenomenon my favorite example
that I'd like to take you through in
detail is another paper that I
co-authored that I was not in charge
here this was done when I was a doctoral
student but it was done by my friend
Nick luden and this was a really fun
paper we did a study in which we looked
at a Collegiate cross country team and
we did this in season which was awesome
so shout out to all you people that
helped out with that as participants
because it's hard to get athletes in
competition to do a study like this and
so we looked at them we did performance
testing BO2 Max muscle biopsies both pre
and post a 3-we taper in season so we
actually did this I think three weeks
before their conference championships
did their post testing right before and
then the data collection actually
happened in their actual races and so
when we say that we saw about a
6% average Improvement in race
performance it was looking at their race
times at conference championships as
well as the three weeks before so what
happened is we let these athletes just
do what ever they were going to do for
their normal taper and they eventually
did uh get to about a 50% reduction in
volume by the third week what that
specifically looked like was week one
they dropped their volume by 27% so
volume is at 73% of peak then it went
from 73% to about 73% and then down to
50% and they did this mostly by reducing
their moderate intensity training so
they kept their high-intensity speed
stuff their race Pace stuff or even
above Race paace they kept their long
slow recovery runs and everything else
in between they cut now we didn't ask
them to do this we just said do what you
want to do and that's basically how they
chose to do it so that's one model of it
for an endurance athlete I already got
to the end here which is to say that
their performance significantly improved
but I think what was most interesting is
despite the fact that they got to a 50%
reduction in mileage per week we tracked
heart rate we tracked all these other
things but I'm kind of just cutting to
the end here we saw no reduction in V2
Max so despite running half the miles
they did not lose their physical fitness
we saw no change or reduction in
numerous enzymes associated with aerobic
metabolism like citrate synthes and a
bunch of other things and more
importantly interestingly we saw a huge
elevation in fast twitch muscle fiber
function we saw about a 7% increase in
fiber size so diameter so 7% hypert of
fast fibers by cutting training volume
in half there was about a 10% increase
in single fiber Force production
velocity went up though wasn't
statistically significant but about 3 or
4% if I remember correctly and overall
power was up about 10% as well and you
will actually see this consistently in
in the literature fast switch muscle
fibers tend to be hyper responsive to
taper we don't really see much in any of
the research on slow fibers but the fast
switch fibers one will do this the
magnitude which I I'll cover in more
detail in a second is pretty standard
with what we found in this particular
study and so you're going to see those
things there and one could argue that's
potentially one of the largest
contributors to that enhanced
performance is the fact their fast
muscle fibers really tend to take off
you will see a large range in the
research as well as in many practical
settings about how people choose to
taper but I'll try to summarize what the
science says right now collectively
basic premise is that we want to try to
reduce fatigue without compromising
Fitness so we see enhanced performance
and we do this by modifying some of
these variables in the following way
first is duration how long should it be
we see success in a range from about 2
to up to 21 days intensity is typically
either maintained or even slightly
elevated now some particular scenarios
will slightly decrease it but that's
context specific and I will give you
those examples a little bit later almost
universally though you'll see about a 40
to 60% reduction in volume context will
will change that some do more in fact
there's some documentation of people
reducing volume by up to 90% And still
seeing performance enhancements but
again spanning the entire breath of
literature you're going to see 40 to 60%
as really really really common numbers
that
happen frequency which is how many days
you know per week are you working out
tends to be the same or slightly reduced
I will tell you personally I generally
don't recommend going to more than a 20%
reduction in frequency think about it
this way if you're normally used to
working out 5 days a week you probably
don't want to cut it down to 3 days a
week or two days a week I don't have
data to back this up it's just been my
personal and coaching experience people
tend to feel sluggish or a little bit
slow or their skill especially if
they're in a skill-based sport like golf
or something like that even running
shooting basketballs your stride feels
off you feel a little bit you just feel
a little bit sloppy so we tend to keep
frequency pretty close if we do drop it
we drop it by about one day so maybe we
cut off one of our sessions if we have
10 workouts in the week we might drop it
to eight or something like that but we
don't want to do too dramatic of a drop
in frequency cuz you just don't feel
great after that if you do all that you
will see somewhere between a 3 to 6%
enhancement in physical performance now
you may be thinking to yourself that's
not much well the reality of it is you
know pick any major race say the Olympic
Games the difference between first and
say fourth or fifth place is probably
like 1 and a half to 2% and so another
way to think about this is all of your
training all of your sacrifice and your
dieting and not hanging out with friends
and working through pain and Rehab all
that can be lost by simply not tapering
appropriately it can be the difference
between winning the gold and not even
making on the podium it's one of the
reasons why I want to talk about this it
is incredibly powerful and a lot of
people Ming these tapers and that's what
results in you feeling great a week
before and then flat on the day of the
race or feeling terrible running through
a race performing poorly and then having
and setting PRS the next
week any athlete or competitor will tell
you like those are one of the worst
feelings you can get it feels terrible
to just bomb on a competition I have
done this personally many times and then
set PRS a couple of days later and
you're like what the heck like where was
that three days ago well this is
potentially one of the reasons why you
missed time to speak a couple of other
broad themes you'll see in the research
one people that tend to benefit the most
from a taper are those coming from the
biggest overload if you've trained hard
for two weeks you probably don't need a
taper right if you had a six weeks of
moderate training you maybe don't need a
taper the ones that have trained either
the longest or the hardest in fact
there's some really cool methods of
taper like Mike Stone has done in his
lab at East Tennessee where they
actually intentionally do
a week or two weeks of really aggressive
overload leading into their taper so
this is actually not their normal
training they even go harder or longer
on that for a short overload then go
into their taper and they see greater
benefits from their taper when doing
something like that you can get in the
details and read his papers and see the
exact
methodologies not for everyone and not
wouldn't work in every single sport but
that's a really good example of
highlighting the point like if you don't
have anything to taper from you not
going to see a taper benefit remember
what we've been talking about what
causes this stuff what's happening to
physiology that should then make sense
of who's going to respond the best to
this if you're doing something like
running your first
5k you probably would benefit from a
couple of days of taper almost surely
but you maybe don't need a 21-day taper
prior of that competition if you've been
training for six weeks you've been
training for four years like we do with
our athletes right now who are getting
ready for Paris of which we've got
multiple in multiple Sports the taper is
actually very long because we've really
been training for 4 years for this
approach okay couple of other things to
think about here you're really not going
to see any benefit from raising your
volume during a taper and in fact
there's enough evidence to suggest it
can hurt and so bringing up volume close
to competition is almost always a bad
idea okay one more time I don't know of
any papers or studies who have ever
shown a benefit from Raising volume
during a taper and I know of many that
have shown negative consequences so
volume seems to be the big one we want
to be paying attention to here now in
terms of intensity one of the things
you'll also see is either you want to
keep that or raise it slightly but no
more than 25% right so that is a large
bump right there and it's almost always
going to come with negative consequences
next thing to keep in mind is if you're
going to keep your intensity the same or
even slightly elevated you have to have
at least a
25% or more reduction in volume okay so
if in your situation you've decided to
keep your intensity and you've only
reduced volume by 10% you're probably
going to see no benefit if however you
only want to reduce your volume by 10%
for whatever reason but you're not
increasing intensity you might be okay
so it's that combination that you want
to avoid either keeping volume or
raising it probably bad only lowering
volume by a little bit but keeping or
raising your intensity also bad okay so
if you're going to keep the volume
around you got to really make sure that
intensity is accounted for or you're
still going to run into problems if you
enjoyed this clip you can watch the full
episode by clicking here
[Music]